Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - [Latin verses at Eton], Pendet Homo incertus gemini ad confinia mundi; 1882 and 1884; poems.lt18
    - [untitled], [between February 1733 and September 1734]; mss.0093; poems.lt18; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 78, 86
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled but under the heading "Carmina", annotated by Gray "Play-Exercise at Eton" and listed in the index at the end as "Knowledge of Himself, Latin Verses at Eton", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 50-51.
  - [Lines Written at Burnham], And, as they bow their hoary tops, relate; 1775; poems.lobt
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 83
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 20
    Written at Burnham and sent in a letter to Horace Walpole, [August 1736]. First published, untitled, in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 24.
    - [untitled], [August 1736]; mss.0096; poems.lobt; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 81, 87
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 26, vol. i, 46-49 (subscription required)
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled, in a letter to Horace Walpole, [August 1736].
  - [Lines on Dr Robert Smith], Do you ask why old Focus Silvanus defies; 1902; poems.lods
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 74
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 280
    Written between 1742 and 1768, prompted presumably by a proposal by Dr Smith to cut down the Chestnut Walk at Trinity College, Cambridge. First published, entitled Lines, in
    Gosse (ed.), Works, rev. ed. (1902), vol. i, 142
    - [untitled], [between 1742 and 1768]; mss.0094; poems.lods; [1?] transcript[?]; [privately owned]
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 79, 86
      A manuscript, here untitled, owned (1902) by Prof. Adam Sedgewick.
  - [Lines Spoken by the Ghost of John Dennis at the Devil Tavern], From purling streams and the Elysian scene; 1915; poems.lojd
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 71-72
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 13-17
    Written at Cambridge by [8 December 1734] and sent in a letter of that date to Horace Walpole. First published, untitled, in
    Toynbee (ed.), Correspondence (1915), vol. i, 13-15
    , referred to as "A Journey in Hades" in
    Northup, Bibliography (1917), item 1221a
    - [untitled], [8 December 1734]; mss.0095; poems.lojd; 3 autograph; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 80, 87
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 4, vol. i, 9-11 (subscription required)
      Autograph, here untitled, in a letter to Horace Walpole, [8 December 1734].
  - A Long Story, In Britain's isle, no matter where; 1753; poems.lost
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 43-48
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 142-152
    Written and revised at Stoke Poges between August and October 1750 when Gray was staying there with his aunt. First published in Dodsley's Designs ( 1753 ), [14].
    - A Long Story, 1750; mss.0097; poems.lost; [?] autograph fair copy, corrected; JHGL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 82, 87
      Whibley, Notes on Two Manuscripts (1937), 55-57
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 605, 10, Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53, 41, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 227, 69
      Autograph fair copy, corrected, wanting ll. 5-8, with marginal explanatory notes.
    - A Long Story, August 1750; mss.0098; poems.lost; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 83, 87
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 28
      Autograph fair copy, here beginning "In Britain's Isle (no matter where)", with marginal side notes, dated "Aug: 1750" and annotated "Printed in 1753 with Mr Bentley's Designs, & repeated in a 2d Edition", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. II, 651-652.
    - [untitled], mss.0271; poems.lost; [?] transcript, partial; YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 411, item I1013
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10625>
      Transcript, partial, headed Lady Schaub and Miss Harriet Speed went one morning...to find Gray the poet and missing of him left a card...to whom he sent these verses.
  - Ode for Music, "Hence, avaunt, ('tis holy ground); 1769; poems.ocmu
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 48-51
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 264-274
    Written at Cambridge between 6 February and 20 April 1769 for the installation of the Duke of Grafton as Chancellor of the University, 1 July 1769. First published, anonymously, as Ode performed in the Senate-House at Cambridge... (1769), a copy of the first edition with an autograph note is at the Henry W. And Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, New York, NY, USA.
    - Ode, for musick, [1769?]; mss.0099; poems.ocmu; 4 autograph fair copy (unsigned); HARV
      Photocopy in RP2338, Manuscripts Collection, The British Library, London, UK
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 85, 87
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 603(?), 9
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36724>
      Autograph fair copy (unsigned), here entitled Ode, for musick, lot 125 in an unidentified sale.
    - Ode, [1769?]; mss.0100; poems.ocmu; 4 autograph fair copy; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 86, 87
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 603, 9
      Catalogue of a Sotheby's sale (30 June 1984), lot 483, facsimile in catalogue
      Rich, Margaret Sherry, "Please forward". E-mail to Mark Farrell, forwarded to the editor, 26 June 2006
      Farrell, Mark, "Re: [Fwd: Please forward]". E-mail to the editor, 28 June 2006
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Ode. A hand-written, nineteenth-century saleroom ticket, which refers to the manuscript as "Lot 603", is stuck onto the last page with sealing wax.
    - An Irregular Ode for Music, 1780[?]; mss.0222; poems.ocmu; 11 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled An Irregular Ode for Music (p. 63) (Ode. VII [p. 65]). The poem, which has numbered stanzas (I.-VIII.) and several annotations to the half-title page, based on information on the title page of the 1769 edition, and to ll. 39, 41, 42, 43, 45, 66, 70, and 84, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], November 1805; mss.0101; poems.ocmu; 1 transcript in the hand of Norton Nicholls, partial [l. 1]; ETON
      Mitford (ed.), Works (1843), vol. v, 50
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 87, 87
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), vol. iii, 1301
      Transcript of l. 1 in the hand of Norton Nicholls, in his MS Reminiscences of Gray, p. 26.
  - Ode on a Distant Prospect of Eton College, Ye distant spires, ye antique towers; 1747; poems.odec
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 7-10
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 54-63
    Written at Stoke Poges c. August 1742 during one of Gray's most productive periods. First published, anonymously, as a folio pamphlet by Dodsley, 30 May 1747.
    - Ode, on a Prospect of Windsor, & the adjacent Country, 1743; mss.0103; poems.odec; 3 autograph fair copy; ETON
      Facsimile in Illustrated London News 132 (20 June 1908), 896
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 88, 87
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Ode, on a Prospect of Windsor, & the adjacent Country, in 1743.
    - Ode. on a distant Prospect of Windsor, & the adjacent Country, August 1742; mss.0104; poems.odec; 3 autograph fair copy, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 89, 87
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 24-25
      Autograph fair copy, revised, here entitled Ode. on a distant Prospect of Windsor, & the adjacent Country and dated "at Stoke Aug: 1742", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol I, 278-279 and continued on p. 284.
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0105; poems.odec; 1 autograph, partial [motto and notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 90, 88
      Autograph of the motto and notes to the poem, untitled but numbered 3. and identified on f. 3r as "3. Ode, on a distant prospect of Eton-College", in MS instructions to Dodsley for the 1768 London edition, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768. The notes were first published in the poem's version in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0106; poems.odec; [1?] autograph, partial [motto and notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 91, 88
      Autograph of the motto and notes to the poem in MS instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - Reflections on Human Life, An Ode, [17??]; mss.0102; poems.odec; 6 transcript in an unidentified hand, two leaves bound with blue publisher's binding paper 230 mm x 160 mm; CARM
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 87
      Johnsen, Mary Catharine, "Gray's Distant prospect". E-mails to the editor, 8 and 19 January 2007
      Transcript, possibly contemporary, entitled Reflections on Human Life, An Ode, Occasion'd by a distant Prospect of Eton: College, where the author was educated. According to a dealer-catalogue ticket on the front paste-down of the little portfolio holding the MS, the MS was initially purchased by William H. Robinson Ltd. Pall Mall by private treaty from the Bibliotheca Phillippica and, according to a pencilled note on the rear paste-down, acquired by Rachel McMasters Miller Hunt in 1953.
    - Ode on a Distant Prospect of Eaton College, 1780[?]; mss.0218; poems.odec; 10 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode on a Distant Prospect of Eaton College (p. 15) (Ode. III. [p. 17]). The poem, which includes the motto (attributed in a different hand to "Menander") on the title page and Gray's note to l. 4, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - On a distant Prospect of Eton & the adjacent Country, mss.0255; poems.odec; 4 transcript c. 220 mm x 184 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/07/2010.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=141906>
      Transcript of the poem in Vol. DCXXXI (a volume of unbound MSS of "Misc. prose and verse") of the Holland House Papers, the papers of the Fox and Fox-Strangways families, Barons Holland and Earls of Ilchester, of Holland House, Kensington.
    - [untitled], July/August 1827; mss.0258; poems.odec; [?] transcript, partial, in the hand of William Pitter Woodhouse 191 mm x 125 mm (volume); HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36730>
      Transcript of the poem, partial, beginning "Say [i.e. Gay] hope is theirs by fancy led", in the hand of William Pitter Woodhouse, in his Commonplace book of verse and prose by various authors, July-August 1827, vol. i (82 leaves), f. 17.
    - An Ode On a distant prospect of Eton College, [between 1749 and 1750]; mss.0263; poems.odec; 9 transcript in the hand of Melesinda Munbee; HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36723>
      Transcript of the poem in the hand of Melesinda Munbee in her autograph Commonplace book ( 1749 - 1750 ), signed, containing poetry in the form of odes, epitaphs, and riddles.
    - Ode on a distant prospect of Eton College, [before 1805]; mss.0287; poems.odec; [?] transcript 290mm x 230mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 1075, item Y0034
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10639>
      Transcript, entitled Ode on a distant prospect of Eton College, in the Frances Boscawen and Julia Evelyn Commonplace Book, a collection of verse by various authors and some original verse, contains about 100 poems copied by the authors, beginning in 1746.
    - Ode on a distant prospect of Eton College, [between 1766 and 1800]; mss.0288; poems.odec; [?] transcript in the hand of James Forbes; YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10638>
      Transcript, entitled Ode on a distant prospect of Eton College, in James Forbes' Commonplace book, 1766-1800, vol. I "Poems on Several Occasions Collected from Different Authors", a manuscript of a collection of approximately 150 poems and excerpts, primarily epitaphs and elegies, poems in praise of virtues, odes dedicated to women, and poems on nature and weather.
  - Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat, Drowned in a Tub of Gold Fishes, 'Twas on a lofty vase's side; 1748; poems.odfc
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 5-6
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 78-85
    Written at Cambridge between 22 February and 1 March 1747 and sent in a letter of that date to Horace Walpole. Mason is the only source for this letter, the poem sent in it has not survived. First published in Dodsley's Collection of Poems by Several Hands, 3 vols, vol. II. (London, 1748 ), 267-269, reprinted in 6 vols, vol. II. (London, 1758 and later edns.), 328-330.
    - On the Death of Selima, a Favourite Cat, who fell into a China-Tub with Gold-fishes in it, & was drown'd, 1747; mss.0108; poems.odfc; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 92, 88
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 26
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 142
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled On the Death of Selima, a Favourite Cat, who fell into a China-Tub with Gold-fishes in it, & was drown'd, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, 381.
    - On a favourite Cat, call'd Selima, that fell into a China Tub with Gold-Fishes in it & was drown'd., [17 March 1747]; mss.0109; poems.odfc; 2 autograph fair copy 236 mm x 183 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 93, 88
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 135, vol. i, 272-279 (subscription required)
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled On a favourite Cat, call'd Selima, that fell into a China Tub with Gold-Fishes in it & was drown'd., in a letter to Thomas Wharton, [17 March 1747].
    - On the Death of a favourite Cat drown'd in a China-Tub of Gold-Fishes, [1757?]; mss.0110; poems.odfc; 2 autograph fair copy 157 mm x 102 mm; MOLI
      Facsimile and description in Verlyn Klinkenborg et al., British Literary Manuscripts, Series I. From 800 to 1800 (New York, 1981), no. 98. Reserve photocopy (microfilm copy) in RP149, Manuscripts Collection, The British Library, London, UK
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 94, 88
      Catalogue of a Sotheby's sale (18 July 1967), lot 537
      Catalogue of a Christie's sale (A. A. Houghton sale, 14 June 1979), lot 234, with facsimile, plate 29
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled On the Death of a favourite Cat drown'd in a China-Tub of Gold-Fishes, annotated on verso in the hand of Carolina Pery "known to be Mr Gray's handwriting about the Year 1757".
    - Ode On the Death of a Favourite Cat, Drowned in a Tub of Gold Fishes, [after 1748]; mss.0107; poems.odfc; 3 transcript in an unidentified hand 180 mm x 120 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Duke Humfrey's, Bodleian Library, on 02/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 88
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. II, 990, item T3395
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=84496>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, stanzas numbered 1.-7., in a volume of copies of verse from various sources, mainly printed, 18th cent., with a list of contents on pp. i, 1-4 (Summary Catalogue, 46462).
    - Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat Drowned in a Tub of Gold Fishes, 1780[?]; mss.0217; poems.odfc; 6 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat Drowned in a Tub of Gold Fishes (p. 9) (Ode. II. [p. 11]). The poem is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - On a favourite Cat called Selima that fell into a China Cistern that had Gold Fish in it, and was Drown'd, [before 1758?]; mss.0238; poems.odfc; 2 transcript in the hand of Mary Capell, "bound in contemporary calf, but with the spine broken, gatherings loose, worn, and with light spotting or dust-staining"; LELI
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=5594>
      Transcript in the hand of Mary Capell, beginning "T'was on a lofty Vase's side", in an autograph manuscript volume "signed by 'Mary Capell' on the first folio. Comprises an anthology of over eighty manuscript poems, of which some are dated from 1740 to 1751, with a six-page index at the end."
    - An ode on a favorite cat called Selima which fell into a china cistern..., [between 1750 and 1780]; mss.0264; poems.odfc; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand 210mm x 170mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 911, item T3301
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10632>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, entitled An ode on a favorite cat called Selima which fell into a china cistern..., in a Commonplace book (c. 1750-1780), in several hands, a collection of over a hundred lighthearted, satirical, and serious poems, primarily on the subjects of politics and women's conduct.
    - On a favorite cat called Selima that fell into a china tub with goldfishes in it and was drowned, mss.0265; poems.odfc; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand; YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10644>
      Transcript, in an unidentified hand, entitled On a favorite cat called Selima that fell into a china tub with goldfishes in it and was drowned.
    - Upon a cat drown[ed] in a china basin in which were goldfish, [before 1805]; mss.0266; poems.odfc; [?] transcript 290mm x 230mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10640>
      Transcript, entitled Upon a cat drown[ed] in a china basin in which were goldfish, in the Frances Boscawen and Julia Evelyn Commonplace Book, a collection of verse by various authors and some original verse, contains about 100 poems copied by the authors, beginning in 1746.
  - [Ode on the Pleasure Arising from Vicissitude], Now the golden Morn aloft; 1775; poems.oopv
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 100-103
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 201-207
    Written probably in 1754 or 1755. First printed privately in 1774. First published, in two versions, among the notes to the poems, entitled Ode, On the Pleasure arising from Vicissitude, and as Ode in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 78-81 (with Mason's additions) and 236-237 (ll. 1-48 only) respectively.
    - Fragment of an Ode found amongst Mr. Grays papers after his decease and here transcribed from the corrected Copy, [after 1771]; mss.0113; poems.oopv; 4 transcript in the hand of William Mason, partial [wanting ll. 17-20]; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 95, 88
      Clark (ed.), Ode on Vicissitude (1933), discussion of Mason's transcript and facsimile of 1774 pamphlet
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, headed "Fragment of an Ode found amongst Mr. Grays papers after his decease and here transcribed from the corrected Copy", wanting ll. 17-20 and accompanied by a list of "Variations in the first copy", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1097-1100. Ll. 21-24 and 69-96 were composed by Mason.
    - [untitled], [after 1771]; mss.0114; poems.oopv; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason, partial [ll. 17-20]; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 96, 88
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 247, notes
      Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 201, notes
      Transcript of ll. 17-20 in the hand of William Mason, within the "Extract from Mr Gray's Pocket Books... 1754", which also contains notes arguably related to the poem, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1110.
    - [?], [17??]; mss.0111; poems.oopv; [?] transcript in the hand of James Beattie 250 mm x 200 mm; UABD
      Transcript in the hand of James Beattie, annotated in his hand "A note which I find in a Memorandum-book of Mr Gray's 1754 will best explain the intended plan of this beautiful Lyrical fragment, and will give the poetical reader how he meant to conclude it. "Contrast between the winter past and coming spring – Joy owing to that vicissitude – many who never feel that delight – Sloth - Envy - Ambition – how much happier the Rustick who feels it though he knows not how.""
    - [?], mss.0112; poems.oopv; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand; [privately owned]
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, owned (1969) by Arthur A. Houghton, Jr.
    - Ode On the Pleasure arising from Vicissitude, 1780[?]; mss.0232; poems.oopv; 11 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.